So today's דף daf is י"א, Yud Aleph, in which we will,
God willing, finish the first פרק perek and move on to the
second. And we pick up with dealing with in what way is
מעילה Me'ilah one of the things that is a mountain suspended by
a hair's breadth. And the גמרא Gemara here, rather than underscoring the
fact that there's not a good פסוק pasuk to base certain things
on, emphasizes the fact that there is that some of these laws
seem to be suspended, you know, sort of on very little in
terms of rational basis. And we're trying to figure out though which
one of them are really the ones that really are very hard,
you know, are that way, and we move up to the following.
The גמרא Gemara says like this. אלא מסיפא, Ela misefa, three lines
from the top of י"א עמוד א', Yud Aleph Amud Aleph, we
discussed the תשובה Teshuvah about somebody taking a beam from הקדש Hekdesh
that does not do מעילה, Me'ilah, but when they hand it to
their friend they do, and that seems arbitrary. If you steal it
from הקדש, Hekdesh, why don't you do מעילה? Me'ilah? And the גמרא
Gemara says, well you didn't exactly steal it, let's say that that's
a special case that you actually were the גזבר. gizbar. And therefore
until you actually give it to somebody else, you haven't really taken
it away from הקדש. Hekdesh. So really though the problem says the
גמרא Gemara is from the end of that ברייתא, braita, which says
the following.
אלא מסיפא, Ela misefa, or excuse me, the end of the משנה.
Mishna. בנאה בתוך ביתו הרי זה לא מעל עד שידור תחתיה בשוה
פרוטה. Bena'ah betoch beito harei zeh lo maal ad sheyadur tachteha bishveh
prutah. So
if somebody takes this beam from הקדש, Hekdesh, which by just taking
it again if they're the גזבר gizbar they have not done מעילה,
Me'ilah, and they build it into their house, so then you still
don't do מעילה Me'ilah until you live under it and you get
benefit, a פרוטה's prutah worth of benefit. So why is the act
of building into the house not a stealing? Obviously getting the benefit
is improperly deriving benefit from הקדש, Hekdesh, but how about the act
of building it into the house? מכדי, Michdi, says the גמרא, Gemara,
let's take a look. שינוי קנה, Shinuy kanah, you changed it, you
transformed it. So that's a way of taking ownership. מאי איריא דר
מאי איריא לא דר, Mai irya dar mai irya lo dar, what
difference does it make if he actually lived in the house or
lived under it or not? היינו כהרים המתלין בשערה. Haino k'harim hamitlin
besa'ara. So that's a mountain on a hair's breadth. Again, these laws
seem relatively arbitrary. Again, noticing that the hair's breadth is the rational
hair's breadth, not necessarily the פסוק pasuk that's the hair. So ומאי
קושיא? Umai kushya? So the גמרא Gemara says, and why is that
exactly bothering you? דילמא כרבא? Dilma k'Rava? We can explain that the
way רבא Rava explains that. דאמר רבא כגון שהניחה פי ארובה, De'amar
Rava kegon sheheniachah pi aruba, that you did not actually nail it
in and cement it in. What you did was you took this
beam and you put it like סכך, sechach, you put it across
your skylight. So you haven't actually transformed it yet. אי דר בה
אין, Ei dar bah in, in that case only if you are
under it and live under it and get some shade from it,
then you've improperly derived benefit and done מעילה. Me'ilah. אי לא דר
בה לא, Ei lo dar bah lo, but otherwise you have not
yet done anything, you're just resting it on the top of your
skylight.
אלא לעולם כדרבא. Ela le'olam k'Rava.
All right, let's go back to what we said yesterday. רבא's Rava
explanation of what was sort of like didn't make too much rational
sense by מעילה, Me'ilah, which is that when the בעל הבית baal
habayit who sent the שליח shaliach to go spend the money in
the store, and then as the שליח shaliach is on his way
to send the money in the store, the agent, the person realizes
that oh my God I gave him the wrong money, I gave
him the הקדש Hekdesh money, so now he's no longer considered an
agent for this person because he no longer wants this person to
represent him and to use the money. And the person does מעילה
Me'ilah although he's completely unaware. So the גמרא Gemara says that's what's
so crazy. How, as the גמרא Gemara said before, this poor שליח,
shaliach, right, שליח עניא, shaliach anya, like this poor guy, why is
he doing מעילה? Me'ilah? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא לעולם כדרבא
דקשיא לך מידי דהוי המוציא מעות הקדש לחולין. Ela le'olam k'Rava d'kashya
lach midi dahavei hamotzi maot Hekdesh lechulin.
And you said, nah, that's not such a new idea. The same
way if somebody accidentally spent הקדש Hekdesh money they do מעילה Me'ilah
even unaware. So here too the שליח shaliach does מעילה Me'ilah unaware.
The גמרא Gemara says no, there's a big difference. התם מידע ידעי
דאיכא זוזי דהקדש. Hatam mida yadi d'ika zuzei d'Hekdesh. In the normal
case of מעילה, Me'ilah, you know that you have funds of sanctified
funds in your house. איבעי ליה לעיוני, Iba'ei lei le'iyuni, and you
need to pay attention to what you're doing. And if you accidentally
take the wrong money purse or use the wrong money, even if
you're unaware, unaware does not mean that you're blameless, you're still negligent.
So there it makes sense that you did מעילה. Me'ilah. הכא מי
ידע? Hacha mi yada? Here,
the poor guy, you gave him money to spend. He had no
right to assume הקדש, Hekdesh, you know what every time before you
give somebody money to spend they're supposed to inquire whether it's הקדש
Hekdesh money? He had no basis of assuming there could be any
problem. And all of a sudden it turns out that he's done
מעילה Me'ilah because of your mistake and then you woke up in
the middle. היינו כהרים המתלין בשערה. Haino k'harim hamitlin besa'ara. So that's
why it's like a mountain suspended by a hair. But again, what's
fascinating here is that it's sort of like biological hair, or if
you want, what the גמרא Gemara is saying is if you want.
or what the גמרא Gemara is saying is this because this is
not so rational and we're not claiming that there's a verse that
tells us this right so therefore that just shows how weakly based
it is on a verse. If we said okay this is a
crazy law but here's the verse that says it so what are
you going to do it's an explicit verse? But the fact that
it's not rational and that there's no verse that's defending it just
shows how weak is its connection to the biblical to the biblical
source.
Yeah I think I was saying like explicitly I can see that
happening he's
like no it's not then like somewhere in the middle he said
oh I don't know yeah but I know yeah I don't think
so because if you anyway. Alright let's take a look. So all
of those are הרים התלויים בשערה harim hatluim besearah and then this
next line which seems to be the clarification of הרים התלויים בשערה
harim hatluim besearah is מקרא מועט והלכות מרובות mikra muat vehalachot merubot
a very small verse and many laws that derive from it.
So many many things that
grow beyond the simple support that they have in the verses. So
the גמרא Gemara says תנא. tana. So now now we have a
ברייתא braita that'll elaborate. Our משנה mishnah mentioned חגיגה chagigah מעילה meilah
and שבת shabbos
was הרים התלויים בשערה harim hatluim besearah a little verse and huge
amount of הלכות. halachos. A ברייתא braita adds some more to that
list. תנא מתנא בברייתא tana matna be'braita נגעים
ואהלות negaim ve'ohalos which are famously known as the most difficult parts
of ש"ס Shas the aspects
of צרעת tzaraat and the sort of leprosy spots or scaled disease
and אהלות ohalos the טומאה tumah that is transmitted through being under
a same roof. מקרא מועט והלכות מרובות mikra muat ve'halachos merubot is
the very few verses and an enormous amount of הלכות. halachos. So
now the point is there is an enormous amount of הלכות halachos
but it would be hard to say that there are few verses.
I mean פרשת פרה parshas parah is usually the one like we're
normally used to the special
פרשיות parshiyos פרשת זכור parshas zachor whatever five פסוקים psukim ten פסוקים.
psukim. פרשת פרה parshas parah takes a while for them to read
that segment right? And נגעים negaim oh my god that's תזריע ומצורע.
tazria u'metzora. So what do you mean it's מקרא מועט? mikra muat?
So the גמרא Gemara says so alright not all of תזריע ומצורע
tazria u'metzora but anyway so the גמרא Gemara says נגעים
מקרא מועט? negaim mikra muat? נגעים negaim is a small number of
verses? נגעים מקרא מרובה הוא negaim mikra merubah hu נגעים negaim has
a lot of verses. I mean again some of the laws the
amount it might be disproportionate the laws to the verses and it
might be that it's not always exactly clear how it derives from
the verses but it's not it's not accurate to say that it's
a lot of laws and few verses. So אמר רב פפא הכי
קאמר amar Rav Pappa hachi ka'amar this is what it means נגעים
מקרא מרובה והלכות מועטות negaim mikra merubah ve'halachot muatot which is also
a little surprising. נגעים negaim has many verses and few הלכות halachot
which is also surprising. What do you mean few הלכות halachot there's
a whole מסכת masechet of it. But okay maybe again maybe the
proportion normally we expect there to be many more הלכות halachos than
biblical verses. I mean for example there's like what three one verse
in the תורה Torah about giving a גט get and there's a
whole מסכת masechet on it. So alright so here you have a
whole פרשה parsha of צרעת tzaraat you have הלכות halachos but maybe
it's roughly proportional roughly even equal. Anyway the גמרא Gemara says that
that would be relatively speaking הלכות מועטות. halachot muatot.
אהלות ohalos is the
opposite מקרא מועט והלכות מרובות mikra muat ve'halachot merubot a few פסוקים
psukim and many הלכות. halachot. Now again here although there's a lot
of פסוקים psukim about dead bodies and becoming טמא tamei and so
on the actual number of verses that talks about the טומאה tumah
transmitted under a roof or being on top of it are relatively
few and there's a lot of הלכות. halachot. Okay so אהלות ohalos
fit into the pattern we've seen before מקרא מועט והלכות מרובות mikra
muat ve'halachos merubot נגעים negaim is in the reverse. Okay so גמרא
Gemara says ומאי נפקא מינה u'mai nafka mina and what why are
you bothering categorizing things which is an interesting question of what's the
point of the whole משנה mishnah but I don't think this is
not now being asked in the context of the משנה mishnah it's
being asked in context of נגעים negaim and אהלות. ohalos. What's the
point of categorizing? Meaning maybe if you want to talk about mountains
on hair-breaths that's important because it communicates again the power of תורה
שבעל פה. Torah she'be'al peh. But what's the value of saying that
נגעים negaim is the opposite? Like what does that categorization do for
me? So the גמרא Gemara says ומאי נפקא מינה u'mai nafka mina
so אי מסתפקא לך מילתא בנגעים ei mistapka lach milta be'negaim so
you should know where to go for your reference. If you have
a question what's the הלכה halacha about certain הלכות halachos of צרעת
tzaraat so עיין בקראי ayein be'krayei don't bother reading the משניות mishnayos
go look at the פסוקים psukim because it's most of the because
the פסוקים psukim are so straightforward and most of the there's more
פסוקים psukim than there are הלכות. halachot. ואי מסתפקא לך מילתא באהלות
ve'ei mistapka lach milta be'ohalos if you have a שאלה shaylah about
אהלות ohalos don't think you're going to get your answer by פסוקים
psukim עיין במתניתין ayein be'matnitin go look in the משניות mishnayos that's
where you'll find your answer. Okay so that's pretty funny right because
certainly
you can't exactly get a הלכה halachic answer from looking at the
פסוקים psukim by נגעים negaim but still maybe what it means is
that before if you want to sort of get your basic parameters
and guidelines and anchoring a good reading and a good understanding of
the פסוקים. psukim. will get you like half of the way there.
And that is true by some things, you know, and by other
things it's not. By other things even if you know the פסוקים,
pesukim, it's like you're still completely at sea in terms of what
הלכה halakha is going to do in terms of defining the parameters.
So, it's interesting. The גמרא Gemara does not ask what's the point
of mentioning the whole phenomenon of mountains supported by a hair? Right
again, maybe that's just to underscore the enormous sort of power of
תורה שבעל פה. Torah she-ba'al peh. But why do you take this
opposite category? Why are we labeling נגעים nega'im as the opposite? As
many פסוקים pesukim and few הלכות. halakhot. And it's telling you, you
know what? Because if you're learning נגעים, nega'im, it would be a
good idea to understand, really understand the פסוקים. pesukim. That will really
help clarify a lot. I have to tell you, I was teaching
in our in our כולל kollel that we started this year, we
were doing עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. And the opening שיעור, shiur, I
was talking to the guys about how in all the discussion in
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah in the משניות Mishnayot and in the גמרא,
Gemara, you don't find you find complete silence by an area that
is very, very dominant in the תורה Torah about its concerns about
עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. And you find absolutely no rabbinic literature on
it, and that is the issue about destroying עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah.
Okay, you find about עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah being אסור בהנאה, assur
be-hana'ah, you find about issues about not worshipping עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah,
you find all these laws relating to עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and
non-Jews in ש"ס, Shas, but you don't find any laws about destroying
עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, which if you've been paying attention during ספר
דברים, Sefer Devarim, is a pretty much of a recurring theme; there's
a lot of verses. So anyway, scholars have discussed it for a
while and basically pointed out that it is not very healthy to
be talking if you're in, you know, ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael under
Roman rule where there are idols, you know, where there are these
idols every sort of, you know, every two feet, to talk about
the מצווה mitzvah to destroy עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. You know, so
all you need to do is say there's a מצווה mitzvah to
destroy עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, but you're פטור, patur, you're an אנוס
oness or whatever, and then one guy gets it in his head
that he's actually going to go ahead and do it, you know?
So anyway, so they don't really discuss it at all.
So anyway, so one of my students was like a little incredulous,
they say, "Really? Come on, you mean to tell me there's nowhere
in the גמרא Gemara which discusses it?" I say, "I really think
there's nowhere in the גמרא Gemara which discusses it." He says, "Here's
what we're going to do." You know, I said, "How do you
find if something doesn't exist?" Right? So I said, "We'll open up
the ספר החינוך, Sefer Ha-Chinuch, because the מנחת חינוך, Minchat Chinuch, if
people know about the אחרון acharon מנחת חינוך, Minchat Chinuch, you know,
he'll quote every like relevant גמרא Gemara related to a particular מצווה.
mitzvah. So let's see if he quotes anything when it comes to
the מצווה mitzvah of destroying עבודה זרה." Avodah Zarah. So we were
opening up the מנחת חינוך, Minchat Chinuch, so first I find it
in the ספר החינוך, Sefer Ha-Chinuch, you know, in דברים, Devarim, and
he says "מצווה mitzvah to destroy עבודה זרה." Avodah Zarah. Now if
anybody knows the structure of the ספר החינוך, Sefer Ha-Chinuch, after he
speaks about the מצווה, mitzvah, then he says "מדיני
המצווה," mi-dinei ha-mitzvah, from some of the laws of the מצווה, mitzvah,
and he gives you some of the laws. So here the ספר
החינוך Sefer Ha-Chinuch said, "מדיני
המצווה," mi-dinei ha-mitzvah, he says, "מדיני המצווה כולם מפורשים
בכתוב."
mi-dinei ha-mitzvah kulam meforashim
ba-katuv.
That's all he says! I don't have to quote any גמרא, Gemara,
it's all in the verses. Okay, end of story. So that sort
of pretty much answered the question, there's absolutely no גמרות Gemorot on
it. So that would be an example of עיין בקרא ayen ba-kera
where there's no תורה שבעל פה Torah she-ba'al peh on something. Yes.
The Persians were who ruled where the בבלי Bavli was compiled. Yes.
While they weren't they weren't exactly monotheists, but they didn't have idols.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, I'm not getting into the discussion. All right, moving
on. I just wanted to give you an example of עיין בקרא.
ayen ba-kera. All right, so anyway, דינים. dinim.
But that statement itself, עיין בקרא, ayen ba-kera, that's a statement of
תורה שבעל פה. Torah she-ba'al peh. Those חכמים chakhamim were deciding
which ones you could just figure out.
Or a hermeneutic itself, that statement.
Right, exactly. Okay, דינים. dinim. After we finish this, I'll tell you
something about what this whole thing, or a theory about what this
whole discussion is doing here in חגיגה. Chagigah. דינים, dinim, so the
גמרא Gemara says, now we get to the last thing which are
דיני עבודות, dinei avodot, טהרות, taharot, טומאות, tumot, etc., which are considered
to be, which have יש להם מה שיסמוכו. yesh lahem mah she-yismokhu.
The opposite of the right, there are three categories. There's היתר נדרים
heter nedarim which are flying in mid-air, have absolutely nothing to support
themselves on. You have these mountains that have a tiny thing to
support themselves on, a hair. And then you have sort of the
normal stuff which has good support in the verses, יש להם מה
שיסמוכו. yesh lahem mah she-yismokhu. Okay? And that now we're going to
look at that list, but even with that, the גמרא Gemara is
going to be a little bit bothered because רש"י Rashi says the
phrase יש על מה שיסמוכו, yesh al mah she-yismokhu, they have what
to support themselves on, does not sound like it's like fully supported.
It does not sound like it's completely self-explanatory in the verses. So
the גמרא Gemara is going to question things on this list and
say, "What do you mean they have something to support themselves on?
Isn't it sort of explicit, you know, these types of laws?" So
let's take a look. All right, so let's take a look. דינים.
dinim. The גמרא Gemara says, "מכתב כתיבן." mikhtav ketivan. What do you
mean? All the you know,
the judgments or whatever
and and דיני ממונות. dinei mammonot. I mean, you have all of
פרשת משפטים. Parashat Mishpatim. I mean, again, not like you don't need
תורה שבעל פה, Torah she-ba'al peh, but it's not like it has
something to support itself on, it's very well supported. So, לא נצרכה
אלא לכדרבי. lo nitzerkhah ela le-khid'rabbi. No, you need it for what
רבי Rabbi teaches.
דתניא, di-tanya, רבי אומר, Rabbi omer, "נפש תחת נפש." nefesh tachat nefesh.
This is if the case where a person is trying to hit
his friend and actually hits... incidentally hits a pregnant woman and it
causes a miscarriage and it says that if the woman actually
died ואם אסון יהיה ונתתה נפש תחת נפש, v'im ason yihye v'natata
nefesh tachat nafesh, okay a soul for a soul. Now of course
this was
unintentional murder; he was trying to hit his friend. I mean it
was negligent but he was trying to hit his friend and accidentally
he killed this woman. So the Rabbis understand that you can't be
put to death for that type of a thing. So what does
נפש תחת נפש nefesh tachat nafesh mean? ממון. mamon. It means that
there's some type of a monetary payment. אתה אומר ממון, ata omer
mamon, you say monetary, או אינו אלא נפש ממש, o eno ela
nefesh mamash, maybe it literally means the person is put to death?
נאמר נתינה למטה ונאמר נתינה למעלה. ne'emar netina lemata v'ne'emar netina lemala.
No because it said to give above; it says when there's a
miscarriage ונתן בפלילים, v'natan biflilim, pay the fine in the court. So
that means monetary payment and here it says ונתתה נפש תחת נפש,
v'natata nefesh tachat nafesh, you shall give soul for a soul. מה
נתינה האמורה למעלה ממון, ma netina ha'amura lemala mamon, the same way
the payment for the miscarriage is a fine is money, אף כאן
ממון, af kan mamon, here too it's money and it's not actually
execution. So that is not פשט pshat of the פסוקים. psukim. I
mean many people would claim it's actually quite interesting that there are
some Bible scholars that claim that
by the time the argument is that you find this type of
thing in the Code of Hammurabi as well, eye for an eye,
tooth for a tooth, and the claim is that by the time
that the Torah was
given this might have been a stock phrase which just refers to
equal justice and was never meant to be taken literally.
You read it in the Code of Hammurabi?
Yeah that's the claim, that's the claim. But anyway the point is
that it is not fully supported, okay? It's something that maybe we
would not have necessarily seen in the verses and therefore it has
what to rely on but it's not fully supported.
עבודות, Avodot, so now
the עבודה, avoda, the service in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, so
my God that's the whole book of ויקרא, Vayikra, at least the
first half of the book of ויקרא. Vayikra. If anything has a
lot of detail it's the עבודה avoda in the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. So the גמרא Gemara says מכתב כתיבא, michtav k'siva, what are
you talking about? That's well written. לא נצרכה אלא להלכות הדם. lo
nitzrecha ela l'halachos hadam. The aspect that there's an idea to convey
the blood to,
or actually more to catch the blood, is not so explicit. דתניא,
dtanya, and we taught in a ברייתא braita והקריבו, v'hikrivu, והקריבו בני
אהרן, v'hikrivu bnei Aharon,
so it says and they shall bring the blood close. This is
after when a sacrifice is slaughtered. זו קבלת הדם. zu kabalat hadam.
So actually although it says to bring close, which means to convey
the blood to the altar, it actually is read by the Rabbis
to mean that one of the acts of the עבודה avoda is
the actual catching of the blood in a basin.
ואפקה רחמנא בלשון הולכה, v'afka Rachmana bilshon holacha,
the Torah referred to the idea of catching the blood, it used
the phrase of conveying the blood
דכתיב והקריב הכהן את הכל והקטיר המזבחה, dechitiv v'hikriv hacohen es hakol
v'hiktir hamizbecha,
by the fat. It says the כהן kohen shall bring all the
fat close and put them on the altar. So you don't catch
the fat; they don't start flying out of the animal after you
שחט. shacht. So והקריב v'hikriv means anyway literally it just means to
bring close. ואמר מר זו הולכת איברים לכבש, v'amar mar zu holachas
evarim lakivash,
that is the bringing of the limbs to the ramp. So if
the word means to convey the blood or the limbs or the
fat,
why do the Rabbis read into this verse of to convey the
idea of catching the blood or what does it mean to say
that that means the catching of the blood? למימרא, l'memra, to tell
you דהולכה לא תפקא מכלל קבלה, d'holacha lo tipka miklal kabala, that
I'm sorry yeah in order to tell you that הולכה, holacha, the
conveying of it, is not sort of excluded from the idea of
catching the blood. Let me just see how what רש"י Rashi means.
Right, meaning that הולכה holacha is not categorically different. Because the גמרא
Gemara says that הולכה holacha is an interesting
עבודה. avoda.
הולכה holacha is an עבודה שאפשר לבטלה. avoda she'efshar l'vatla. You can
שחט shacht the קרבן korban right near the מזבח, mizbeach, catch the
blood and throw the blood and never do the act of conveying
it from where the קרבן korban was to being near the מזבח.
mizbeach. So you might think that because it's an עבודה avoda that
you could do without that even if you are doing it it
does not have the full status of an עבודה. avoda. And the
relevance would be let's say a non-כהן kohen did it. Let's say
you were doing the הולכה holacha and you had a thought of
פיגול, pigul, if everybody remembers when we did קדשים, Kodashim, פיגול pigul
is a big dominant concern. So maybe oh it's only הולכה holacha
it doesn't matter הולכה holacha you didn't even have to do. No
if you actually are doing הולכה holacha it counts as an עבודה
avoda even though in theory it would be possible to do it
without. doing the הולכה. holacha. So that's why the word הקריבו hikrivo
which is talking about the rabbis' understanding to be talking about catching
the blood, we're saying it uses the verb for conveying the blood
to tell you that the act of conveying is just as important
and just as much of an עבודה avoda as the act of
catching the blood. So that whole little דרשה drasha again that's nowhere
clear in the פסוקים, psukim, this idea and therefore that is seen
as something that is not supported but not fully supported. Again like
it's so funny, I mean my god you have all of מסכת
זבחים, Masechet Zvachim, like how many you know dozens of if not
hundreds of laws could we list that are things that are not
fully supported in the verse? So again I really have a hard
time explaining like why the גמרא Gemara is picking the particular thing
it's doing, what's the whole logic that's dictating this, I don't really
know. But anyway טהרות, Taharos, okay. Now aspects about purity and impurity.
מכתב כתיבן, Michtav Ketivan, come on טומאה וטהרה tuma v'tahara is one
of the most dominant things of the laws that are written in
the תורה. Torah. It says and there actually you gotta admit that
a lot of those the details are pretty clear. I mean again
you need some clarity but a lot of the details are present.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, לא נצרכה אלא. Lo nitzrecha ela.
By the way I should point out that you know you could
say the whole premise here is you could challenge. You could say
when the משנה Mishna says things like the דינים, dinim, טומאה וטהרה,
tuma v'tahara, עבודות avodos are יש להם על מה שיסמוכו yesh lahem
al ma sheyismachu it means are well supported. Doesn't mean have some
support. You could say it means actually emphasizing that it's the opposite,
they're well supported. But the גמרא Gemara is choosing to read it
that they're somewhat supported and therefore has all of its problems. So
let's take a look. So טהרות Taharos it's written. No, לא נצרכה
אלא לשיעור מקווה Lo nitzrecha ela l'shiur mikva דלא כתיב. delo ktiv.
Here's something that's not so clear in the תורה. Torah. What is
the minimum size of a מקווה? mikva? דתניא Detanya we learn in
a ברייתא braita ורחץ בשרו במים verachatz b'saro bamayim you should the
person should wash your flesh with water which is understood to mean
immerse yourself במי מקווה. b'mei mikva. So the water means water of
a מקווה. mikva. You could say right there that's not written explicitly.
The literal sense of the verse is take a bath right? Wash
yourself with water. But okay that we're not saying is the חידוש.
chiddush. That means a מקווה. mikva. את כל בשרו Et kol b'saro
all of your flesh. מים שכל גופו עולה בהן. Mayim shekol gufo
oleh bahen. So that has to mean water that can cover your
whole body. That's the minimum size of a מקווה. mikva. וכמה הן
V'chama hen and how much is this? אמה על אמה ברום שלוש
אמות. Ama al ama berum shalosh amot. An אמה ama by an
אמה ama like a foot and a half by a foot and
a half by four and a half feet.
ושיערו חכמים מי מקווה ארבעים סאה V'shiru chachamim mei mikva arbaim se'ah
and the rabbis estimate you know sort of not estimated but like
determined you know that quantified that that was forty סאה se'ah that
is the minimum size of a מקווה. mikva. So therefore that is
why that is not explicit, that exact minimum size. Again I would
say what's more not explicit is the idea that we're talking about
a מקווה mikva altogether rather than washing yourself. By the way now
תוספות Tosafot asks a question why do you say only three אמות?
amot? Right a person even though people were shorter in the past,
they really were, they weren't just four and a half feet although
some Jews were even closer to that, but okay anyway, four and
a half feet is a little bit short so what do you
mean that's enough? So the basic answer, he has a lot of
different discussions: you bend your head, you do this, but the simple
answer that he says in one place not here I think is
water displacement. If you have right a thing that has a foot
and a foot by three and a half feet if you've got
higher walls even if the water only goes to four and a
half feet and you go in it the water's going to fully
cover you, right? So you don't need water that's your height, right?
Because you'll go in and the water will rise above you.
All right anyway what how many gallons was forty סאה? se'ah? I
used to I used to get how many gallons?
Yeah I did once before, I don't know. Anyway all right so
טמאות Tameot right טמאות. Tameot. So that's about being טהור. tahor. How
about becoming טמא? tame? מכתב כתיבן, Michtav Ketivan, that's also in the
verse. So the גמרא Gemara says לא נצרכה אלא כעדשה מן השרץ.
Lo nitzrecha ela k'adasha min hasheretz. The size of a lentil bean
of like a rodent is the minimum size that causes טומאה. tuma.
So here again the aspects of minimum sizes are things that are
not clear in the פסוקים, psukim, right? The whole idea of שיעורין
shiurin is something that you know the sort of that the rabbis
use to define minimum quantities but they're not explicit. So דלא כתיב
Delo ktiv it's not written.
Isn't lentil bean being הלכה למשה מסיני? Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai?
Right it's הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai, it's not in the
פסוק. pasuk. That's the whole point.
Yeah that's the point here. Yeah.
דתניא Detanya it says in a ברייתא braita בהם. bahem. So it
says I so it says כל הנוגע בהם kol hanogea bahem anybody
who touches them these rodents יכול בכולם yachol bekulam maybe you have
to touch the whole thing or the whole thing has to be
present for you to be טמא. tame. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar מהם.
mehem. Another verse says if some of them אשר יפול מהם אל
תוכו. asher yipol mehem el tocho. If something of them falls into
a vessel. So of them not all of them. יכול במקצתן Yachol
bemiktzatan so maybe even the tiniest bit of it causes טומאה. tuma.
תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar בהם bahem them the entirety. הא כיצד Ha
keitzad so how do you satisfy these two verses?
עד שיגיע במקצתו שהוא ככולו. Ad sheyagia bemiktzato shehu kechulo. It's enough
to only touch a portion of it, only a portion has to
be present, but it has to be representative of the whole. So
what's a small amount that's representative of the whole? שיערו חכמים כעדשה
Shiru chachamim k'adasha the size of a lentil
bean שכן חומט. sheken chomet. A certain type of a of a
rodent is starts off is born it's only the size of a
lentil bean, so that's the smallest amount that represents the whole thing.
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda says, כזנב הלטאה. Keznav haleta'ah. Actually,
the size of a lentil bean is like the size of the
tail of a lizard. Now why does the tail of a lizard
representative of the whole? Because if you cut off the tail of
a lizard, the גמרא Gemara says, it says in other places, it'll
still thrash around even after it's... even though it's cut off from
the animal. So that's a type of a thing that has some
life to it, so it's a size of something that represents the
whole even though it's not the whole. Okay, so that's טמאות. Tame'ot.
עריות, Arayot, now forbidden sexual relations, again, my God, if you wanted
an out, look, I mean, for example, I want to just show
you why it's so funny the questions that the גמרא Gemara is
asking. If I were to ask you, which are the areas in
the תורה Torah that get the most treatment in terms of like
the details, you know, and the הלכות Halachot and so on? Well
I just mentioned one which isn't mentioned here, which is destroying עבודה
זרה. Avoda Zara. Fine, but besides that, what are things that get
detailed treatment? I mean שבת Shabbat gets talked about a lot but
not details. If you were to ask me what has a lot
of details, I would first and foremost say the first half of
ויקרא, Vayikra, which is the עבודות, Avodot, the second half of ויקרא,
Vayikra, which is, right, which is a combination of גילוי עריות Gilluy
Arayot and...
and טמאות וטהרות, Tum'ot v'Taharot, right? And maybe פרשת משפטים, Parshat Mishpatim,
which is דינים. Dinim. So everything that's listed here are the things
that get the most detailed treatment in the תורה. Torah. So it's
funny that the גמרא Gemara chooses to read this as somewhat supportive.
פשט Peshat of the משנה Mishnah is these are the ones that
are the most detailed treatment in the תורה. Torah.
That's
that's so revealing the way you just framed it. In other words,
the חכמים Chachamim want to make certain that the places where you
actually have the most פסוקים, Pesukim, its meaning has to be mediated
by תורה שבעל פה, Torah SheBe'al Peh, by the חכמים Chachamim themselves.
Right. In other words, you could otherwise conclude, the things that really
are very sparsely described, that's our purview. No, quite the contrary. You
can't read the most detailed sections.
So that's why the בבלי Bavli is choosing to read the משנה
Mishnah this way to underscore that even these, right.
It's a good point, it's a good point.
Again, I'm not sure if it's פשט Peshat in the משנה, Mishnah,
but I'll concede that that might be what's going on in the
בבלי. Bavli. Okay, fine. Yes.
For example, it looks like the forbidden sexual relations is very clear,
but next מסכת Masechet we're going to have a discussion about what
is sex.
Right, of course, and it's so also funny then why it chooses
to give the answers it gives, because there's still so many other
things it could have given. Okay, עריות, Arayot, נכתב כתיבן, Nichtav ketivan,
isn't that pretty explicit? No, נצרכה לאנוסה דף י"א עמוד ב', Nitzrecha
l'nusa d'ap yud-alef amud bet, בתו מאנוסתו. Bito me'anusato.
Somebody's daughter, now again, we just had before a very disturbing גמרא
Gemara about rape being less of a
מעוות Me'uvat than consensual sex in the case of adultery without paying
attention to the harm of rape. So here similarly, the גמרא Gemara
wants to say, to describe the idea of somebody's biological daughter who
is not their wife's daughter, because the תורה Torah explicitly forbids sex,
it says אשה ובתה, Isha u'bitah, you cannot marry a woman and
her daughter, right? But that's specifically the daughter of the woman you're
married to, whether it's
your biological, man's biological daughter or not, it specifically refers to a
man's wife and her daughter. In terms of where it does not
refer to one's wife, but just a man's biological descendant, it only
refers to granddaughter. It says, what's the פסוק Pasuk it
says? ערות בת בנך ובת בתך. Ervat bat bincha u'bat bitecha. The
nakedness of your the daughter of your son or your daughter of
your daughter. So there, no mention of wife, just of your biological,
but it mentions granddaughter, it doesn't mention daughter. So the question is
how do you know daughter? So we need a special derivation. So
that's what we're going to look at. But what's problematic is is
that in describing the phenomenon of biological daughter who is not your
wife's daughter, the גמרא Gemara calls it בתו מאנוסתו, Bito me'anusato, the
daughter who from your rape, from your act of rape. That's what
it says. I mean why did it say, it could have even
said, you know, there's another word from אנוסה, Anusa, which is מפתה.
Mefuta. It could have said a woman that a man seduced. Okay,
so maybe I don't know, you know, I don't know like why
it chose to describe the phenomenon of biological daughter who is not
your wife's daughter as a case of אנוסה Anusa and not a
case of מפתה. Mefuta. Again, you know, does he
have to marry her to become his wife according to the תורה
Torah or...?
No, only in very particular cases, you know.
Doesn't she have to give the... doesn't the father...
what? No, but that's a case of a נערה, Na'arah, it could
have been a
non-נערה, Na'arah, but... all right, maybe you're right, maybe that has something
to do with it, אנוסה Anusa even more so, אנוסה Anusa by
the מפתה Mefuta you have more of a choice about whether to
marry, the אנוסה Anusa you're obligated to, so that doesn't explain...
No, אשה ובתה ishah u'vitah means a wife and her daughter, but
בת בתה bat bitah בת בנה bat binah is referring to biological.
Okay. So לביתו מאנוסתו, le'bito me'anusato, a man's daughter from his the
woman he raped, again, it really just it really includes the category
of biological daughter who's not his wife's daughter, דלא כתיבא,
de'lo ketiva,
it's not written, granddaughter's written but not daughter, דאמר רבא אמר לי
רבי יצחק בר אבדימי אתיא הנה הנה אתיא זימה זימה. de'amar Rava
amar li Rabi Yitzchak bar Avdimi atya hena hena atya zima zima.
We make a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah from the words הנה הנה
hena hena and זימה זימה zima zima to connect the case of
granddaughter to the case of wife and daughter to say that even
in the case of biological without being a wife's daughter, daughter is
included. And the two דרשות drashot of הנה הנה hena hena and
זימה זימה zima zima is one to include the prohibition and one
to include the punishment. Okay. הן הן גופי תורה, hen hen gufei
Torah, these are the essence of the Torah. So הני אין הנך
לא? hani in hanach lo? Now again, this gets back to the
discussion we just had before because the simple read of that phrase
is this last category where it's where it's where it's שיש להם
על מה שיסמוכו she'yesh lahem al mah she'yismokhu are all of these
detailed laws, הן הן גופי תורה. hen hen gufei Torah. These are
the essence of the Torah, the body of the Torah. So that
makes it sound like these, the ones with all the verses, are
the bodies of the Torah, not the earlier ones. So the גמרא,
Gemara, and that's a very dangerous statement. So the גמרא Gemara says
הני אין הנך לא? hani in hanach lo? What, only this last
category is real Torah, not the earlier stuff? אלא אימא הן והן
גופי תורה. ela eima hen ve'hen gufei Torah. No, the point is
these and they, everything in this משנה, mishnah, whether in the first
category, the middle category, or the last category, it's all the essence
of Torah and that's really making quite the other type of a
statement. And that's what we end this פרק. perek. הדרן עלך כל
החייבין. hadran alach kol ha'chayavin. Now what the heck is this משנה
mishnah doing in this
מסכת? masechet? So you could say well חגיגה Chagigah is mentioned, a
lot of things are mentioned. חגיגה Chagigah is the one that's sort
of most un-obvious in that whole list. So I was looking and
then we're about to start a next פרק perek which is, I'll
just read you the first line, right, אין דורשין בעריות בשלשה ולא
במעשה בראשית בשנים. ein dorshin ba'arayot be'shlosha ve'lo be'maaseh bereshit be'shnayim.
This is the part of חגיגה Chagigah that everybody knows where it
gets into all of this אגדתא. agadata. We're going to talk about
the people that you know, ארבעה נכנסו לפרדס arba'ah nichnesu la'pardes and
the whole sense of mysticism and you know what is all that
stuff doing here in the middle of חגיגה? Chagigah?
So I looked at the Albeck's
משנה mishnah yesterday because he sometimes has interesting like scholarly notes or
framing for things and his claim is, he doesn't say anybody else
who says this, but his claim is that this is all a
commentary on the previous משנה. mishnah. The previous משנה mishnah if you
remember spoke about if you didn't bring your קרבנות korbanot on the
רגל, regel, it's מעוות לא יוכל לתקון, me'uvat lo yukhal litkon, a
perversion that cannot be corrected. And then it ended with whoever it
was that was רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah or
somebody who said that no, you don't say מעוות me'uvat unless something
was fixed to begin with, so what's מעוות לא יוכל לתקון? me'uvat
lo yukhal litkon? It was a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham that was
שפירש מן התורה. she'piresh min haTorah. So he says so his claim
is that these two משניות, mishnayot, last משנה mishnah of this פרק
perek and the one we're about to read, are telling you where
is the danger of being פורש מן התורה. poresh min haTorah. Like
if somebody's פורש מן התורה, poresh min haTorah, where could he wind
up going wrong? So one area is well you've got all these
mountains that are suspended on a hair, right, you could easily come
to question those or to be misled by that that it doesn't
have strong biblical verses. And then in this פרק perek you're going
to get all the things that you're not supposed to you know
דרשן, darshan, you're not supposed to sort of learn except under very
limited and well-defined parameters and that it's very dangerous to be learning
this. So if you're a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham שפירש מן התורה,
she'piresh min haTorah, here are the areas you could go astray. So
I don't know, I thought that was an interesting explanation. It's as
good as any other because it's really quite bizarre what this משנה
mishnah we just read and the משנה mishnah we're about to read
are doing in this מסכת. masechet. So let's take a look. Noting
that and I'm open to any better answers to that question, let's
now start the second פרק perek and this gets into like I
said the part of חגיגה Chagigah that most people know about. So
אין דורשין בעריות בשלשה. ein dorshin ba'arayot be'shlosha. One cannot explicate, talk
about, again, אין דורשין ein dorshin has a sort of technical turn
and it does really seem to be in conversation with the previous
משנה mishnah about the derivation of verse because לדרוש lidrosh mostly means
to explicate the הלכות, halakhot, you know, that derive from the verse,
to sort of be דורש doresh the verse. Okay, you start with
the verse and you unpack the verse. That's to be to actually
come up with the learn already הלכות. halakhot. Yeah, right. So the
act of deriving from the verse, that's דורשין. dorshin. So that is
seems very connected to the earlier משנה mishnah which is basing things
basis on the verse. Okay, so you don't do this in a
group of three. ולא במעשה בראשית בשנים. ve'lo be'maaseh bereshit be'shnayim. And
you'll well I will we'll talk about that. And you don't discuss
or derive you know meanings of the acts of creation with two
people. ולא במרכבה ביחיד. ve'lo be'merkavah be'yachid. And not in acts of
the divine chariot, the vision in יחזקאל, Yecheskel, even but with one
person, אלא אם כן הוא חכם ומבין מדעתו, ela im ken hu
chacham u'mevin mi'da'ato, except the one exception would be in the case
of מעשה מרכבה maaseh merkavah if somebody... is wise and can figure
things out more or less on his own and you don't really
have to go into much detail. כל המסתכל בארבעה דברים, Kol hamistakel
b'arba'ah devarim, now anybody looks at the following four things, now our
גרסא girsa is רטוי לו ratui lo כאילו לא בא לעולם, k'ilu
lo ba l'olam, which is a bizarre word, so some versions of
the משנה Mishnah have ראוי לו. ra'ui lo. Rashi's גרסא girsa is
רטוי לו, ratui lo, but Rashi explains that the word more or
less means ראוי לו. ra'ui lo. Okay, so anyway, it's fitting for
him is that you never even came into the world if you
tried to explore four areas. מה למעלה מה למטה, Mah l'ma'alah mah
l'matah, what's above, what's below. מה לפנים מה לאחור, Mah l'fanim mah
l'achor, what's in front, what's behind. Question whether the front and behind
means spatially or means timewise. There's, you know, what happened before the
world was created, what will happen at the end of time. מה
למעלה מה למטה, Mah l'ma'alah mah l'matah, what's above the heavens, maybe
what's, you know, what's below the earth. That presumably that means spatially
to the degree that when we talk about heavens and the angels
in heaven we can talk about spatial, but at least metaphorically that's
spatially. Back and front and back is a question whether it means
like spatially or whether it means or whether it means timewise. וכל
שלא חס על כבוד קונו, V'chol shelo chas al kvod kono, and
anybody who did not have, you know, concern to try to protect
the honor of his creator because he's exploring these things that should
not be explored. רטוי לו שלא בא לעולם, Ratui lo shelo ba
l'olam, again it's fitting that this person never came into the world.
Now again, what are exactly these types of things that are being
so protected? I mean, we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara, but just
to sort of share with you that what, you know, my research
last night, which the whole research consisted of opening the Artscroll משנה.
Mishnah. But okay, he claims that a lot of these are the
areas where the Gnostics were, really had their like focus and expertise
to try to explain, like look at the story of creation and
explain the exact sort of dynamics of how the world was created,
even aspects of the עריות, arayot, I was completely unaware of this.
He said that the Gnostics actually, you know, attacked the אברהם יצחק
ויעקב Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov by saying how they transgressed like איסורי עריות,
issurei arayot, you know, that יעקב Yaakov married two sisters and, excuse
me, יעקב Yaakov married two sisters and I don't know and יצחק
Yitzchak married his sister. Yeah, so whatever it was, there was a
whole critique of the אבות avot with relating to עריות arayot and
he thinks maybe that's some of what's going on. But the point
is, but what's the interesting insight is, and maybe this would have
been pretty obvious anyway, but he says identifying with the Gnostics that
these types of areas of exploration might for some have been דווקא
davka the area that is the most important religious type of intellectual
pursuit and you know and that's the highest level and only for
the initiate whatever. And here the גמרא Gemara is actually saying that
that actually is like the least appropriate type or the one that
you have to be the most careful about and that to do
it in a certain degree actually compromises the honor of the creator.
So again, it's interesting to just raise that question of was there
a particular sect or group, you know, that the Rabbis had in
mind here or were they just thinking about these pursuits in themselves?
So he reads וכל שלא חס על כבוד קונו v'chol shelo chas
al kvod kono is in all these people are those who are
not חס. chas. Yeah, I think that the general, no, the general
reading is וכל v'chol meaning, meaning that maybe there are others, but
that basically מה למעלה מה למטה mah l'ma'alah mah l'matah etc. is
a prime example of לא חס על כבוד קונו. lo chas al
kvod kono. But let's see in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמרת ברישא ולא במרכבה ביחיד. Amart b'reisha
v'lo b'merkavah b'yachid. Now here gets to Michael's question. When it says
you don't do it with three, does that include the teacher or
not? So the גמרא Gemara initially assumes that it includes the teacher.
So there can't be three including the teacher. So when you get
to say that you can't do the acts of the divine chariot
with one, that means yourself, nobody's allowed to learn it, because if
we're including the teacher, then nobody can learn it. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אמרת ברישא ולא במרכבה ביחיד, Amart b'reisha v'lo b'merkavah b'yachid,
even an individual by himself can't learn מעשה מרכבה. Ma'aseh Merkavah. והדר
אמרת אלא אם כן היה חכם ומבין מדעתו, V'hadar amart ella im
kein hayah chacham u'meivin m'da'ato, unless you know what you're talking about.
Well, of course, the only one who would be able to learn
it by himself would be somebody who would know what he was
talking about. So what does that mean? גמרא Gemara says no, הכי
קאמר. hachi ka'amar. So you're right, it doesn't mean three the whole
group, it's three the number of students. אין דורשין בעריות לא בשלושה,
Ein dorshin b'arayot lo b'shloshah, in a group of three, but לשלושה
lishloshah to three students. ולא במעשה בראשית לשניים, V'lo b'ma'aseh bereishit lishnayim,
and you can't do מעשה בראשית Ma'aseh Bereishit to two students. ולא
במרכבה, V'lo b'merkavah, and you can't teach מרכבה, merkavah, the divine chariot,
ליחיד l'yachid to an individual student, אלא אם כן היה חכם ומבין
מדעתו, ella im kein hayah chacham u'meivin m'da'ato, unless the guy you're
teaching you can like hint to him and he can figure most
of it out by himself. But we're not talking about the total
size of the group, we're talking about the number of the students.
I should also pause for a second here and just tell you
the way רמב"ם Rambam reads all of these גמרות gemarot because all
of these are clearly seem to be turning us into like, you
know, mystical areas and so on, although it is an interesting question
whether מעשה בראשית Ma'aseh Bereishit the גמרא Gemara understood meant like a
mystical understanding of creation or really just understood like no, let's really
figure out, you know, cosmologically what happened, how, you know, you have
פסוקים, psukim, well let's be. scientists, let's or whatever, let's try to
understand just physically how was the world created? So מעשה בראשית Maaseh
Bereishis might make, might have had a more sort of, you know,
not physical as opposed to a metaphysical meaning, but certainly מעשה מרכבה
Maaseh Merkavah is understood, you know, mystically and we're going to see
the גמרות Gemaras about that. But it's worth noting now and the
רמב"ם Rambam consistently in later stories in the גמרא Gemara understands these
all very rationally. He says מעשה בראשית Maaseh Bereishis is basically, you
know, physics, science, astronomy is included, everything about how the world, the
physical science of the world, and how the world was created and
all, but also how the world runs, you know, physics, astronomy, all
of that, and מעשה מרכבה Maaseh Merkavah is theology, is, but it's
the rational understanding, you know, and philosophical, you know, exploration of God.
So it's very, it's interesting to be aware that the רמב"ם Rambam
takes this גמרא Gemara and these terms and sort of reads them
through a very Greek philosophical rational lens, and we'll see how some
of that will play out as we continue. Okay, let's take a
look, let's go further. אין דורשין בעריות בשלושה. Ein Dorshin Ba'arayot Bishlosha.
One does not explicate or, you know, derive the details of the
aspects of עריות, Arayot, which we just, you know, in a group
of to three students. Meaning you have to have fewer or more?
Fewer, fewer, because you don't want people to be distracted and not
catch things. It has to be a very small group. So even
in מסכת יבמות, Masechet Yevamot, we're going to have a really small
דף Daf session? Right, exactly. מאי טעמא, Mai Ta'ama, what's the reason?
אילם משום דכתיב Ilem mishum d'chtiv איש איש אל כל שאר בשרו,
Ish ish el kol shear besaro, each person to his, you know,
flesh should not have sex with his relative. איש איש תרי, Ish
ish trei, so איש איש Ish ish is two men. שאר בשרו,
Shear besaro, so חד, chad, that's the third person, the relative, the,
I mean, okay. ואמר רחמנא Ve'amar Rachmana לא תקרבו לגלות ערווה, Lo
tikrevu l'galot ervah, you should not come close to expose ערווה, Ervah,
so here's a nice little play, exposing the meaning of the verses.
So if you've got a group of three students, you should not,
you know, expose issues of עריות Arayot to them. אלא מעתה, Ella
me'ata, if that's what it is, you're basing it on that type
of a read of the verse? So דכתיב d'chtiv the verse says
איש איש כי יקלל אלוהיו, Ish ish ki yekalel elohav, any man
who curses his God, ואיש איש אשר יתן מזרעו למולך, Ve'ish ish
asher yiten mizaro l'Molech, if a person gives over his child to
the מולך. Molech. הכי נמי, Hachi nami, would you also read that
like somehow you can only discuss issues of like עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah with two people because it says איש איש? Ish ish? Of
course it doesn't say לא תקרבו Lo tikrevu there, but okay. אלא
היי מיבעי ליה, Ella hai mibaei leh, no, איש איש Ish ish
is telling you something else there, לרבות את הנוכרים שמוזהרים על ברכת
השם. Lerabot et hanochrim shemuzharim al birkat Hashem. The first one about
cursing God is to tell you that even the non-Jews, any איש,
ish, any person, is prohibited against blaspheming God. It's one of the
שבע מצוות בני נח. Sheva Mitzvot Bnei Noach. And how about איש
איש אשר יתן מזרעו למולך, Ish ish asher yiten mizaro l'Molech, the
one about עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah? Same point, דעל עבודה זרה, d'al
avodah zarah, that non-Jews are also prohibited against עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah,
another one of the שבע מצוות בני נח, Sheva Mitzvot Bnei Noach,
כישראל, ke'Yisrael, like a Jew. So איש איש Ish ish just means
any person. האי נמי מיבעי ליה, Hai nami mibaei leh, לרבות את
הנוכרים שמוזהרים על העריות כישראל, lerabot et hanochrim shemuzharim al ha'arayot ke'Yisrael,
that's the third of the מצוות Mitzvot of the שבע מצוות בני
נח Sheva Mitzvot Bnei Noach is forbidden sexual relations. So all of
these איש איש, Ish ish, whether by עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah or
by blasphemy or by forbidden sexual relations, is not coming to tell
you the number of students you can learn this with. It's coming
to tell you anybody, even non-Jews, are included in this category. So
forget those verses. אלא מדכתיב, Ella mid'chtiv, let's try another verse. ושמרתם
את משמרתי, Ushmartem et mishmarti, you should observe my, you know, safeguard.
And this is also said in the context of עריות. Arayot. ושמרתם,
Ushmartem, you plural should observe, תרי, trei, that's two people. משמרתי, Mishmarti,
my area of like my safeguard, חד, chad, one. Okay, that makes
three. ואמר רחמנא Ve'amar Rachmana לבלתי עשות מחקות התועבות, l'vilti asot mechukkot
hato'evot, not to do like these things. So meaning if you have
three people, the way you preserve
the protect the thing so that it doesn't get perverted is, and
that you should not do like those nations did, is by being
careful once you've got three people already not to talk about it.
אלא מעתה, Ella me'ata, if that's true, דכתיב ושמרתם את השבת, d'chtiv
ushmartem et haShabbat, ושמרתם את המצוות, ushmartem et hamitzvot, ושמרתם את משמרת
הקודש. ushmartem et mishmeret hakodesh.
It says about guarding in a lot of places. הכי נמי, Hachi
nami, would you say in those places too there's a limit to
how many people you can talk הלכה Halacha about in those areas?
אלא אמר רב אשי, Ella amar Rav Ashi, מאי אין דורשין בעריות
בשלושה? mai ein dorshin ba'arayot bishlosha? Okay, so you know what it
means? Here's what it means. אין דורשין בסתרי עריות. Ein dorshin b'sitrei
arayot. It doesn't mean just you don't like explicate the straight הלכות,
halachot, which by the way would be bizarre if you want people
not to transgress you want them to know the הלכות. halachot. So
now the גמרא, Gemara, it's funny to even think what the
גמרא'ס Gemara's הוה אמינא hava amina was, but now the גמרא, Gemara,
you know, what else did the גמרא Gemara think it meant? But
here the גמרא Gemara says clearly it means you don't sort of
explicate the, you know, the
subtle stuff, the hidden stuff, the non-obvious stuff.
That's a nice play on לגלות, l'galot, it's hidden.
That's a good point too. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason?
סברה הוא. Svara hu. And now forget פסוקים. pesukim. Let's get to
the heart of the matter. Okay,
it's סברא. sevara. בי תרי, Bei terei, if you have two students,
כי יתבי קמי רבייהו ki yasvi kamei ravaihu and they're in front
of their רבי, Rebbe, חד שקיל וטרי בהדי רביה chad shakil v'tari
bahadi rabai so one will have get into a nice discussion with
the with the רבי, Rebbe, ואידך מצלי אודניה לגמרא v'idach matzli udneih
l'gemara and the second guy will be like leaning his ear to
learn, you know, he might not be directly involved in the conversation,
but he's there all along so he's obviously what else is he
going to do except listen in to the conversation? בתלתא, Ba'telasa, if
you've got three students, חד שקיל וטרי בהדי רביה chad shakil v'tari
bahadi rabai one is in a conversation with the רבי, Rebbe, והנך
תרי v'hanach terei the other two are playing on their iPhone... oh
no... שקלו וטרו בהדי הדדי shaklu v'taru bahadi hadadi so they are
having a little conversation amongst themselves, right? That never happens, where the
teacher is teaching and two students are having a little side conversation.
I'm going to have to see you separately! So anyway, so once
you've got three people, you might have two of them in a
little conversation by themselves and they will mishear some of this information.
And because it's so subtle and because it's not obvious, that's going
to lead to an actual a wrong, you know, a wrong הלכה
halacha and acting incorrectly in the area of עריות. arayos. Now of
course the point is you could say that about everything. There's a
lot of very weighty הלכות. halachos. Maybe I shouldn't teach הלכות שבת
Hilchos Shabbos with more than three people because people come to do
things that they that they shouldn't be doing on שבת, Shabbos, they'll
have misunderstood me. So the גמרא Gemara says: אי הכי, I hachi,
כל התורה כולה נמי? kol haTorah kulah nami? So say that about
everything in the תורה, Torah, you know? No, עריות שאני. arayos shani.
No, no, no, עריות arayos is different. דאמר מר, De'amar mar, גזל
ועריות נפשו מחמדתן gezel v'arayos nafsho mechmadtan ומתאוה להן. u'mitavah lahen.
When it comes to stealing, taking things that don't belong to you,
right, which is like, you know, the desire to possess, or when
it comes to sexual desire, these are things that a person's soul
really, you know, you know, has a covets and and has a
lusting for. Which basically means and the גמרא Gemara is making a
pretty profound statement, you know, about subconsciously if we really want something,
we will find a way to act a little bit have misheard
what was exactly said. Not necessarily consciously, but if there's a real
יצר הרע yetzer hara to for this whole area, then you have
to be super careful that people understand exactly and precisely what you're
saying because there's a it's quite possible that subconsciously they'll have the
you know, they'll be motivated to not precisely hear what you are
saying and to mishear.
אמר מר, Amar mar, do you see this as a תנא? Tanna?
Is it a תנא? Tanna? No... אמורא Amoraic statement?
Yeah, it could be either.
Someone said something we're just going to pull it in for conversation.
Exactly, exactly.
So the גמרא Gemara says: אי הכי, I hachi, if that's true,
גזל נמי? gezel nami? So laws relating to theft also should be
you should not teach except to a small group of students at
a time. So the גמרא Gemara says: No, עריות בין בפניו בין
שלא בפניו נפיש יצריה. arayos bein befanav bein shelo befanav nafish yitzreih.
When it's sexual desire, whether the object of the desire is in
front of the person or not, the person still has a strong
desire for it. גזל לא, Gezel lo, בפניו נפיש יצריה שלא בפניו
לא נפיש יצריה. befanav nafish yitzreih shelo befanav lo nafish yitzreih. When
it comes to taking possession of, you know, stealing, possession of things
that are not yours, mostly that's more when you are confronted with
the object of your desire, not when you are not. So here
everybody's in a classroom, right, they're not being confronted with the, you
know, with the Porsche that they want and they're not seeing the
object of their sexual desire. Is that desire still functioning subconsciously to
lead to a mishearing? So the גמרא Gemara says: Well, in areas
of sex it actually is. You know, even if they're not in
the presence of the object of the desire...
It doesn't mean enforcement across, meaning...
Yeah, well, there's a only the things where you might actually legitimately
mishear. Okay, so it's a very interesting psychological insight right in this
גמרא Gemara about how our, you know, the things that we desire,
you know, subconsciously could factor even if we're well-intentioned, you know, to
that we didn't exactly hear what we needed to hear, you know,
and that that's a real risk. And that the difference about the
types of things we, you know, we have desires for when we
are sort of presented with the objects of the desires and things
we have sort of those desires sort of are, you know, even
at other times as well. Okay, so that's the explanation for עריות.
arayos. לא במעשה בראשית בשנים. Lo b'ma'aseh bereishit bishnayim. Now that was
about הלכה. halacha. Now we get to areas not about הלכה, halacha,
areas where the very study of it itself might be considered somewhat
dangerous. So let's take a look. Not in areas of creation with
to two students. You know, you can only do a one-on-one. מנא
הני מילי, Mina hanei mili, where's this from? דתנו רבנן, Detanu rabanan,
our Rabbis taught: כי
שאל נא לימים ראשונים,
Ki she'al na l'yamim
rishonim, we've if now, you know,
if you were to ask about the earlier days. So כי שאל
ki she'al is in the individual. יחיד שואל, Yachid sho'el, an individual
can ask about the earlier days. ואין שנים שואלין, V'ein shnayim sho'alin,
but two cannot. You can't ask two students about this. יכול ישאל
אדם קודם שנברא עולם, Yachol yishal adam kodem shenivra olam, maybe you
can ask even about what came before the world was created, right,
מה לפנים... mah l'fanim... or מה לאחור mah l'achor I should say...
תלמוד לומר... Talmud lomar... You'll ask from the day that about from
the day that the human being was created.
So you can't ask before מעשה בראשית, ma'aseh bereshit, only starting of
the
day of creation. יכול ישאל אדם yakhol yishal adam מששת ימי בראשית?
misheshat yemei bereshit? Maybe you can't ask about the first five days
of creation, right, of you know, whatever, because it's only starting from
when אדם Adam was created. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, לימים ראשונים אשר
היו לפניך. l'yamim rishonim asher hayu lefanecha. No, the early days, the
first days that were before you, before human beings. So you're allowed
to ask before humans were created with one person, that is, starting
from the act of creation, but it can't be before the world
was created. So again, that's an individual can learn מעשה בראשית, ma'aseh
bereshit, but even an individual can't ask מה לפנים מה לאחור, ma
lifnim ma l'achor, what preceded. So you can teach a single person
מעשה בראשית, ma'aseh bereshit, but you can't go into this realm of
before מעשה בראשית. ma'aseh bereshit. יכול ישאל אדם מה למעלה מה למטה
מה לפנים מה לאחור? yakhol yishal adam ma l'ma'ala ma l'mata ma
lifnim ma l'achor? So here it is saying it again, maybe you
are allowed to ask if when when you are dealing with one
person who is being taught and it is allowed to be taught
to one person, maybe you can even go and explore questions of
what's above and below and before and after? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar,
ולמקצה השמים ועד קצה השמים, u'lemiktzeh hashamayim v'ad ketzeh hashamayim, from one
end of the heaven to the other end. ממקצה השמים ועד קצה
השמים אתה שואל, mimiktzeh hashamayim v'ad ketzeh hashamayim ata sho'el, from one
end of the heaven to the other end you can ask, ואי
אתה שואל מה למעלה מה למטה מה לפנים מה לאחור, ve'ee ata
sho'el ma l'ma'ala ma l'mata ma lifnim ma l'achor, but you can't
ask what's before and after and what's above and below and before
and after. And again, this sounds like it's a spatial point, that
you can't sort of ask, you know again, what's above the heavens,
again, whether that's really understood by them spatially or at least that
was the metaphor, you know, or what's outside of the universe, right?
Like that's the sort of question like I know when I was
a kid, you know, and you sort of and you learn like
you know that Einstein taught that what is it, you know, that
that sort of that space like what is it folds onto itself?
Like the galaxy is like finite, right? Space is curved, right? So
the question is, well then what's outside of the space, right? So
I still don't have an answer to that question.
And the scientific answer is that's not an admissible question.
Not an admissible question.
Not something that can be addressed empirically.
Okay, so that would be an example of... exactly, that would be...
so that would be a spatial question. What's outside of the universe,
you know? Okay, so that's understood spatially, or it could be understood
spatially as a metaphor about like, you know, what's above the heavens,
you know, the heavens where the angels preside, or you know, something
about the God's realm and so on. And also the מה לפנים
מה לאחור ma lifnim ma l'achor could be spatial, could be time.
Right, what existed before the world was created? Okay, so let's just
read one more line of גמרא, Gemara, top of יב עמוד א.
yud-bet amud aleph. השתא דנפקא לן מלמקצה השמים ועד קצה השמים, hashta
dinfka lan mimiktzeh hashamayim v'ad ketzeh hashamayim,
now that you've learned the limits of legitimate exploration to be from
one end of the heaven to the next, למן היום אשר ברא
אלהים אדם על הארץ למה לי? l'min hayom asher bara Elokim adam
al ha'aretz lama li? Why do you need the other verse that
limits it from the day of creation, which we also said sort
of limits that you can't ask what existed before creation, now we're
dealing more with time than spatial? Okay, but if the idea of
the edge of the heaven to the other edge limits you spatially
and time-wise to the legitimate areas of exploration, why do you need
this verse of אשר ברא אלהים אדם על הארץ? asher bara Elokim
adam al ha'aretz? No, that's... you're right, you don't need it. That
teaches you something else, לדרבי אלעזר, l'Rabbi Elazar, like Rabbi Elazar. דאמר
רבי אלעזר, d'amar Rabbi Elazar, אדם הראשון מן הארץ עד לרקיע, Adam
harishon min ha'aretz ad larakia, the the first human being was created,
he was so big, he went from the from the earth to
the heavens. That's how tall he was. שנאמר למן היום אשר ברא
אלהים אדם על הארץ ולמקצה השמים, she'ne'emar l'min hayom asher bara Elokim
adam al ha'aretz u'lemiktzeh hashamayim, it really needed to quote the next
two words. God created human on the earth to the edge of
the heaven. Okay, that's how it's reading the verse by chopping it
up that way. So the human being was huge when he was
created. וכיון שסרח, v'kevan she'sarach, once he sinned with the עץ הדעת,
Etz HaDa'at, הניח הקדוש ברוך הוא ידו עליו, heniach Hakadosh Baruch Hu
yado alav,
God put his hand on אדם, Adam, ומיעטו, u'mi'ato, and shrunk him.
שנאמר אחור וקדם צרתני, she'ne'emar achor vakedem tzartani,
front and back you have created me, meaning there was a pre-creation
and a post-creation, ותשת עלי כפכה, vatashet alai kapecha,
and you put your hand on me. So this is the idea,
you know, obviously it could be understood as a metaphor, the greatness
of the human stature, and then after the sin how it shrunk.
And we'll read just one more line like this. אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, אדם הראשון מסוף העולם ועד
סופו היה. Adam harishon misof ha'olam v'ad sofo haya. Not only was
he he wasn't from the ground to the heavens, he was so
big that if he would lie down, he would go from one
edge of the world to the other edge of the world. שנאמר
למן היום אשר ברא אלהים אדם על הארץ ולמקצה השמים ועד קצה
השמים, she'ne'emar l'min hayom asher bara Elokim adam al ha'aretz u'lemiktzeh hashamayim
v'ad ketzeh hashamayim, when God created man on the world on the
earth from one end of the heaven to the other end. That's
again how it's being read that that's describing the creation. So that's
how big he was. So the גמרא Gemara says וכיון שסרח, v'kevan
she'sarach, once he sinned, הניח הקדוש ברוך הוא ידו עליו, heniach Hakadosh
Baruch Hu yado alav, God put his hand on him, ומיעטו, u'mi'ato,
and shrunk him, שנאמר ותשת עלי כפכה. she'ne'emar vatashet alai kapecha. Okay.
אי הכי, ee hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara, now we have two
two ways of reading the verse. One that says that he was
as tall from the earth to the heaven, and the other says
that he reached from one edge of the heavens to the next.
So קשיין קראי אהדדי, kashyan kra'ei ahadadi, the verses contradict themselves. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אידי ואידי חד שיעורא הוא. idi v'eidi chad
shiura hu. No, it's the same distance. The distance from the earth
to heaven The distance from one edge of the heavens to the
next edge of heavens. Okay, we'll end with that. We will continue
tomorrow to discuss things we're not supposed to be discussing. See you
tomorrow. My question is, if we're not supposed to
be discussing this, then why is
it in the גמרא? Gemara? The גמרא Gemara is allowed to talk
about it, but the משנה Mishna says that we're not allowed to
discuss the מעשה בראשית. Maaseh Bereishit.